<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Forfeitures of Londons charter, or, An impartial account of the several seisures of the city charter together with the means and methods that were used for the recovery of the same, with the causes by which it came forfeited, as likewise the imprisonments, deposing and fining the lord being faithfully collected out of antient and modern historys, and now seasonably published for the satisfaction of the inquisitive, upon the late arrest made upon the said charter by writ of quo warranto.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18801</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12112436</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12112436</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54234</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39971)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54234)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 68:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Forfeitures of Londons charter, or, An impartial account of the several seisures of the city charter together with the means and methods that were used for the recovery of the same, with the causes by which it came forfeited, as likewise the imprisonments, deposing and fining the lord being faithfully collected out of antient and modern historys, and now seasonably published for the satisfaction of the inquisitive, upon the late arrest made upon the said charter by writ of quo warranto.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author and are to be sold by Daniel Brown ... and Thomas Benskin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 36 illegible on film.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  Charters, grants, privileges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54234:1"/>
            <p>THE FORFEITURES OF Londons Charter, Or an Impartial Account of the SEVERAL SEISURES OF THE City Charter, Together with the Means and Methods that were uſed for the Recovery of the ſame, with the Cauſes by which it came forfeited, as likewiſe the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, Depoſing, and Fining the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Sheriffs, ſince the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third to this preſent Year, 1682. Being faithfully collected out of Antient and Modern Hiſtorys, and now Seaſonably Publiſhed for the ſatisfaction of the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, upon the late Arreſt made upon the ſaid Charter by Writ of <hi>Quo Warranto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Benskin</hi> in St. <hi>Brides</hi>-Church-Yard, 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:54234:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54234:2"/>
            <head>Since the Charter was granted to the Antient and Famous City of <hi>London</hi> by <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, and other Kings of this Realm, we find ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Inſpections have been made into it, and that at ſundry times the Priviledges and Charter of the ſaid City hath been taken away and ſuſpended; The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Relation of which, as it is Recorded by the moſt Authentick of our Engliſh Writers. Being now thought ſeaſonable and uſeful, is intended to be the Subject of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <p>TO begin at the 50 year of the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1265. Upon the Citizens taking part with the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and the Barons, againſt the King, after the ſaid Earl was Slain at the Battle of <hi>Everſham,</hi> and the King again was reſtored to his Royal Dignities, he began to call to mind how the Citizens had ſhut their Gates againſt him and ſuccour'd his Enemies, ſo that calling a Parliament at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> about the Nativity of the Bleſſed Virgin, in the year aforeſaid, all the Statutes that had been made by the Parliament the Barons had Aſſembled at <hi>Oxford</hi> were Repealed, and alſo all ſuch as had favoured the Barons, and were as then either in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or abroad ſhould be disinherited: It was alſo ordain'd, and paſſed the Aſſent of both Houſes, that many of the Wealthieſt Citizens of <hi>London</hi> ſhould be caſt into Priſon, and the City ſhould be deprived of the Liberties and Priviledges that had been formerly granted and confirmed to them; as likewiſe that all the Chains and Poſts ſhould be pulled up and taken away, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to leave the Streets fenceleſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was no ſooner En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54234:3"/> but put in Execution, for the chief Citizens were Arreſted and committed to Ward within the Caſtle of <hi>Windſor,</hi> till they ſhould pay ſuch Fines as were demanded, which was 300 pounds a peice at leaſt, whereupon the Liberties of the City, purſuant to the ſaid Act, were ſuſpended, and the Tower of <hi>London</hi> forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Outworks for its better Security, as likewiſe ſuch Poſts and Chains as had been brought out of the City, were placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Defences in nature of Barracado's; not long after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parliament was called at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> wherein a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſuch as had been aiding to the Barons, had their Lands confiſcated, which Lands the King no ſooner ſeized, but he gave them to ſuch as had faithfully ſerved him in the Wars, ſo that a conſiderable number, as well of Citizens as others, were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiged to Compound with ſuch as had the Donation beſtowed upon them.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe and ſuch like proceedings of the King, the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners</hi> thought it their ſafeſt way to ſubmit to the Kings Mercy, and after long attendance, and at the inceſſant Intreaties of ſuch Noble Perſons at Court as they could make their Friends, they obtained a Pardon, though many of the Commoners refuſed to joyne with the Mayor and Aldermen, and other Wealthy Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens therein, being rather inclined to ſtand it out, and held ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Debates about defending the City againſt the King, but their Reſolutions in that affair were by moſt of the wiſeſt ſort held as pernicious and dangerous to the Peace and Tranquility of the Nation: The reaſon that induced them to ſuch obſtinacy as moſt conjecture, was becauſe the City at that time was Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by ſundry Nations, who, during the Inteſtine Broils, had been admitted as Citizens to defend the ſame, but in the end, all thoſe Debates and Conſultations came to no effect, for when every Man had ſpent his Verdict, it was thought the ſafeſt way to ſubmit to the Kings Pleaſure, and conſent to what he ſhould think fit, upon which Submiſſion, and a Fine of 20000 Marks, the King received them again into his Favour, and ordered, that ſuch Lands, Houſes, and other things as had been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54234:3"/> and not diſpoſed of, ſhould be reſtored again to the Owners.</p>
            <p>After which, he did not deliver them the poſſeſſion or keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the City as formerly, but placed Sir—<hi>Othon</hi> as Cuſtos or Guardian of the ſame, who was alſo Conſtable of the <hi>Tower:</hi> he likewiſe choſe to be Bayliffs, or as they are now called Sheriffs, <hi>John Adrian</hi> and <hi>Walter Henery</hi> Citizens: The King proceeded yet farther, and compelled the moſt ſubſtantial a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them to give their Sons as Pledges or Hoſtages, thereby to prevent any Revolt for the future, which Pledges or Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he cauſed to be kept in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and maintained at the Coſt of their Parents; as likewiſe by advice of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, he conſtituted a Captain in every County, (now called by the name of Lord Lieutenant) to ſuppreſs any Rebellion that might ariſe upon the diſtaſt of the unruly multitude.</p>
            <p>The King having all this while continued in the City, the better to have an Eye upon, and keep in awe ſuch as upon the aforementioned occaſions were ever now and then ready to make Inſurrections, and upon his departure ordained Sir <hi>John Lind</hi> and <hi>John Waldren</hi> Governours in his Abſence, by the Names of Seneſchals or Stewards, but ſuch earneſt Suits were made by the <hi>Londoners</hi> to obtain a free Pardon, that in the end, after the ſaid Guardians or Governours had taken ſufficient Security for the payment of the Fine of 20000 Marks, the King granted them his Charter of Pardon under the Great Seal and ſent it them, wherein he freely remitted and pardoned all Treſpaſſes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences that had been committed by them during the War, only the Lands, Houſes, Goods and Perſons which he had given to Prince <hi>Edward</hi> his Eldeſt Son, were excepted.</p>
            <p>This Charter of Pardon and Reſtauration of the Cities Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Priviledges, and Immunities, was dated at <hi>Northampton</hi> in the 50 Year of his Reign, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1266. upon which the Seneſcal was diſcharged, and the Citizens choſe then for Mayor <hi>William Fitz Richards,</hi> and for Sheriffs <hi>Thomas de la Fourd</hi> and <hi>Gregory de Rockſledge,</hi> and had the mannagement of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54234:4"/> the City intire as ever, ſo that Trade began to flouriſh, and the Companies began to Incorporate, but this happineſs laſted not long, for in the 52 year of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1267. The King being abſent in the Country, the Earl of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> taking great diſpleaſure for that he might not have his Will, as well for Baniſhing of Strangers, as for Reſtitution to be made unto ſuch as had been disherited, he began to raiſe new Tumults, for having raiſed a great power in the Marches of <hi>Wales,</hi> he came directly for <hi>London,</hi> pretending at firſt as if he came to aid the King in his intended War with <hi>France,</hi> upon which plauſible pretence, he obtained leave of the Mayor and Citizens to paſs through the City into <hi>Southwark,</hi> where he En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped, and ſhortly after Sir <hi>John de Evilli</hi> came and joyned him with about 2000 Horſe and Foot, upon which, and ſome other Actions that had happened, the Mayor cauſed the Bridge and Water-ſide to be guarded Day and Night with ſuch Forces as could be raiſed, and the Draw-bridge to be drawn up every Night, but within a while, the Earl uſed the Matter ſo, that he was permitted to Lodge within the City with a conſiderable number of his men, and getting into favour with ſuch as bore moſt ſway, he by degrees got all his Army to Quarter there, and having thus taken poſſeſſion, he got the Keys of all the Gates, and ſet a Guard of his own men to Watch them, upon which the Popes Legate, who had fled to the <hi>Tower</hi> for ſafety came out, and exhorted the Earl to deſiſt his Rebellious Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but in vain, for the Earl not only commanded him to return from whence he came, but likewiſe gave ſtrict charge to ſuch as kept the Guard on that ſide, that no Proviſion ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be carried into the Tower, notwithſtand about 2000 perſons were got into it, reſolving to defend it. for the King till ſuch time as he Arived with ſuch Forces as he had gathered in <hi>Cambridge-ſhire</hi> and other places adjacent.</p>
            <p>Upon the great abuſes that were at that time uſed towards Strangers, a conſiderable number of <hi>Jews,</hi> with their Wives and Children, got likewiſe into the Tower, and had one quarter of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54234:4"/> at aſſigned them, to defend which, they did very Manfully, ſo that many of the <hi>Londoners</hi> fearing new Inſurrections might be occaſioned by ſuch proceedings, went out of the City, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with them the greateſt part of their Subſtance, and what they left behind them was ſeized by the Earls command, who ſuffered his Men to ſpoil it at pleaſure.</p>
            <p>The greater part of the Commons of the City took part with the Earl, which highly offended the King, and the more, for that they (being as it were without Government) tumultuouſly Aſſembled at <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> and there choſe for their Mayor Sir <hi>Richard de Colworth,</hi> and for Bayliffs <hi>Robert de Linton</hi> and <hi>Roger Marſhal,</hi> diſcharging the Sheriffs of their Places, Offices, and Truſts, contrary to the deſires and endeavours of the more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and Judicious part of the Citizens, and carrying on their outrages yet farther, they forc'd divers Aldermen and chief Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to Priſon without Law or Proceſs, and having them in ſafe Cuſtody went to their Houſes, where they not onely defaced them, but took their Goods and ſpoyled them, under a pretence of Sequeſtration; as likewiſe all that had been Impriſoned within the City Priſons upon the Quarrel of the Barrons, they ſet at Liberty.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe tumultuous Actions were at <hi>London,</hi> the King lay at <hi>Cambridge</hi> with a conſiderable Army to hinder the Rovers that had fortified the Iſle of <hi>Ely</hi>) from making Incurſions on that ſide, notwithſtanding they committed many outrages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing emboldened ſo to do, by reaſon of the <hi>London</hi> Tumults, as well knowing they would oblige the King to draw off his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and ſuch of them as were not intercepted by the Kings Forces, frequently came to joyne with the Earl, doing great Miſchiefs by the way; by whoſe aſſiſtance the Earl being much encouraged, undertook to aſſail the <hi>Tower</hi> which held for the King, in which was the Popes Legate, and a great number of Armed men, as is before recited, upon the firſt News of which attempt, the King diſlodged his Army and Marched towards <hi>London,</hi> but finding his Power too weak, he was obliged to ſell
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54234:5"/> his Plate and Jewels to raiſe more Forces, whereupon he ſent Prince <hi>Edward</hi> and others into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> to raiſe them, and again retired to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where he continued till the Prince came to him with an Army of 30000 <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King upon this Recruit, leaving a ſufficient power at <hi>Cambridge</hi> to defend thoſe parts from the Rovers, advanced with all diligence towards <hi>London,</hi> reſolving to give the Earl Battle, (if he durſt leave the City to meet him) ſending a Herauld to give him notice of his intent.</p>
            <p>When he was come to <hi>Windſor,</hi> he there Encamped, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to inform himſelf how affairs ſtood in the City, and how the people ſtood inclined, not wanting many Loyal perſons there to give him ſecret Intelligence what happened from time to time; he had not long ſtayed at <hi>Windſor,</hi> but his Army daily encreaſed, which made <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and his Party begin to doubt of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Succeſs with which they had flattered themſelves, and thereupon were very deſirous of Peace, but the King would not hearken to their Propoſals, whereupon they appointed to give him Battle upon <hi>Houndſlow-heath,</hi> but the King coming thither with his whole Army at the day appointed, found that they had altered their reſolutions, no perſon being there to oppoſe him; after he had ſtayed ſome time, and underſtood by his Scouts that no Army approached, he ſet forwards towards <hi>London,</hi> and wheeling about, brought his whole Army to <hi>Stratford,</hi> where he gave command they ſhould Encamp.</p>
            <p>In the mean while a Party of the Rebels that Quartered in <hi>Southwark</hi> went to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where they de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtroyed the Church and much defaced the Abby; then coming to the Kings Pallace and finding it diſſerted, they broke open the Gates and plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, breaking all the Windows, and defacing the Images or Statues, ſcarce forbearing to ſet it on Fire; they likewiſe Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſeveral other great Houſes about <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the King lay thus Encamped at <hi>Stratford,</hi> there came to him from beyond the Sea the Earls of <hi>Bullogne,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54234:5"/> 2000 Men at Armes; alſo there Arived in the <hi>Thames</hi> a Fleet of great Ships with a conſiderable Supply of <hi>Gaſcoines,</hi> which lay before the <hi>Tower</hi> waiting the Kings command, to oppoſe whoſe Landing <hi>Glouceſter</hi> drew Trenches and raiſed Bullworks, but when no Man hoped for Peace, by the mediation of the King of <hi>Almaigne,</hi> the Lord <hi>Philip Baſſet</hi> and others, the King conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Treaty, wherein the Ordinance of <hi>Killingworth</hi> was in all points obſerved, and in that Treaty of Peace the <hi>Londoners</hi> were comprehended and taken into favour upon condition that they forthwith payed 1000 Marks to the King of <hi>Almaigne</hi> for the Burning his Houſe at <hi>Thiſleworth,</hi> and the Officers that had been diſplaced during the Tumults, to be reſtored to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Truſt, and ſuch as had been wrongfully Impriſoned, to take their courſe at Common-Law againſt ſo many of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors as they could Learn were concerned therein.</p>
            <p>In the 51 year of the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1377 the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> uſing the Kings Authority, directed Warrants to all the Lords and Barrons, Knights and Burgeſſes that 15 days after St. <hi>Hillary</hi> they ſhould be preſent at <hi>London,</hi> there to Aſſemble in Parliament, to adjuſt matters appertaining to the Publick Weel of the Kingdom, to this Parliament came <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Burdaux</hi> (Son to <hi>Edward</hi> the black Prince, and Grand-Child to the King) accompanyed with a great number of Knights and Gentlemen, and was received by the <hi>Londoners</hi> after the beſt manner, being preſented with many Rich Gifts, as likewiſe his Uncle the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> ſeemed to Honour him above the reſt, placeing him in the Chair of State and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to demand that they would give the King two Tenths in one year, or elſe of all the Merchandice that were ſold in <hi>England</hi> for one year 12 pence of every pound, of every Fire-Houſe one Penny, and of every Knights Fee one Pound of Silver, which demands the Duke earneſtly Proſecuted, ſaying they of neceſſity muſt grant one of theſe Points, for that the Enemies had Proclaimed War, and would ſuddainly Invade the Realm, upon which the Parliament deſired time to debate the matter,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54234:6"/> when as the day appointed for delivering their Opinions was come, one Mr. <hi>Hungerford</hi> was elected to deliver their Opinions who had been (if at that time he was not) the Dukes Steward, though ſome were of Opinion that Sir <hi>Peter de la Moor</hi> was the fitteſt Man on that occaſion, but theſe latter being few in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber they prevailed nothing.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were doing the Duke proceeded, yet farther and demanded a Subſidy of the whole Clergy, which ſo thoroughly netled the Biſhops, that they mightily oppoſed it, but the Duke conſulting with one <hi>Wicliffe,</hi> who greaaly Inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Clergy, he affirmed that it was lawful not only for the King but for Temporal Lords, to take the Goods of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-men towards their Subſiſtance if neceſſity required it, the better to effect this by pleaſing the Biſhops, he Treated with the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to call a Convocation, which was accordingly done, and <hi>William Wickam</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> who had been Baniſhed ſeveral Miles from Court, was by the Dukes order brought there to this Convocation, it was ordained that the aforeſaid <hi>Wicliffe</hi> ſhould appear to anſwer for his ſpreading his Doctrine throughout the City, and in other places, as likewiſe giving his Opinion to the Duke in prejudice to the Clergy, and that being Tryed and Convicted for the ſame, he ſhould undergo ſuch Penaltys as that Aſſembly ſhould think fit.</p>
            <p>And on the 15 of <hi>February</hi> in the year aforeſaid the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation being Aſſembled, he was brought forth by the Dukes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and as he came he was greatly annimated, by ſuch of his followers as had embraced his Doctrine and Councelled nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fear the Biſhops nor the great concourſe of People, ſeeing not only the Duke, but likewiſe all the Nobillity preſent, were his Friends, when he came into our Ladys Chapple in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>Henry Peircy</hi> chief Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> willed him to ſit down and in a manner compelled him ſo to do, ſaying, that he had much to anſwer, and therefore ought to ſit, upon which the Biſhops were highly offended, the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54234:6"/> name of all the reſt, alledging that ſince he was come as a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal to anſwer before his ordinary to ſuch things as ſhould be objected againſt him, he ought to ſhew more Reſpect and Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Convocation.</p>
            <p>The Duke being preſent, and hearing the words of the Biſhop began ſharply to reprehend him, Swearing that he would pull down not only his Pride, but that of all the Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> and added, that although he Truſted in his Parents, they could profit him nothing, to which the Biſhop replyed, that he neither Truſted in his Parents, nor in the Life of any Man, but in God only, in whom he ought to truſt. This laſt anſwer ſo Inraged the Duke, that he Whiſpring the Biſhop ſoftly, <hi>told him, he would rather draw him out of the Church by the Hair of the Head then ſuffer ſuch things at his Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Londoners</hi> who were all this while waiting in Crouds without, hearing how the Duke had threatned their Biſhop, gave a Loud Shout, Swearing, <hi>that they would rather looſe their Lives then any violence ſhould be offered to their Biſhop in his own Church,</hi> and that which heightened their Fury the more was, that the Duke being <hi>Preſident</hi> in Parliament, where the day before it was requeſted in the Kings name that from that day forwards there ſhould be no more Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> but that a Captain ſhould be appointed, and that the Marſhal of <hi>England</hi> as well in the City as in other places, might Arreſt ſuch as offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with many other things which were mannifeſtly againſt the Libertys of the City.</p>
            <p>The Morrow after the <hi>Londoners</hi> Aſſembled themſelves to take Councel what they ſhould do in ſuch a ſtrait they were like to fall into, in caſe a Captain ſhould be choſen, they concluing their Liberties muſt be no longer continued, eſpecially if the Marſhals Office extended it ſelf within their Juriſdiction, and farther, they argued what might be done in Reperation of the affront or Injury put upon their Biſhop, and whilſt they were debating theſe matters and differing in Opinions about coming to a concluſion what to do, the Lord <hi>Fitz Walter,</hi> and Sir <hi>Guidio
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54234:7"/> Brian</hi> entered the City, whether to know their minds or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is uncertain, but the unruly Multitude conſtruing things in the worſt Senſe, were hardly reſtrained from falling upon them, nor had they eſcaped the Hands of the Multitude had not they Sworn they came not in the leaſt to perjudice the City, when having no ſoonor obtained belief and pacified the Rabble, but the Lord <hi>Fitz Walter</hi> ſtood up and made an Oration, the effects of which was, that <hi>whereas he being by Antient Inheritance, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Bearer to the City, was to take Injuries offered to them as to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and thereupon willed them to look to their Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had no ſooner ended but they run to their Arms, every one taking what came next to hand, and in a great rage went to the Inn where the Marſhal lay, breaking open the Doors and ſearching all parts of the Houſe where they imagined he might be, but not finding him, they brought out a Priſoner whom they found there in Fetters and ſet him at Liberty, and then went to other places in Queſt of the Marſhal, but found him not, for that day he and the Duke Dined with one <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Ipre,</hi> of which they were Ignorant, but they ſuppoſed at leaſt to have found them at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and thereupon many of them came with all expedition thither, in the mean while one of the Dukes Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants advertized his Lord what had happened, and adviſed him to Shift for his ſafety, whereupon in a great Fright he left his Proviſion and Fled by Water to his Mannor at <hi>Kennington,</hi> where finding the Princeſs and the Young Prince, <hi>viz. Richard</hi> of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> Son to <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Black</hi> Prince, he related what had happened and grievouſly complained againſt the Inſolency of the <hi>Londoners,</hi> the Princeſs having heard what ſtirs were abroad, comforted him, and told him that, ſhe would do her endeavour to compoſe the difference.</p>
            <p>By this time the <hi>Londoners</hi> underſtanding that the Duke and his accomplice Sir <hi>Henry Piercy</hi> were Fled in great Fury, haſted to the <hi>Savoy,</hi> where meeting a Prieſt, who demanded what the matter was, they told him, that they went to ſeaſe the Perſons of the Duke and Sir <hi>Henry Piercy,</hi> that thereby they might compel
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54234:7"/> them to deliver up Sir <hi>Peter de la Moor,</hi> which they unjuſtly detained in Priſon, upon the hearing of which, the Prieſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>that Sir</hi> Peter de-la Moor <hi>was a Traytor to the King and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be Hang'd;</hi> upon which words (ſo unſeaſonably Spoken) the Multitude cryed out, <hi>That it was</hi> Piercy <hi>in Diſguiſe, that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to</hi> England, <hi>and that his Speech betray'd him, though he had changed his Habit,</hi> and thereupon they ſo belaboured him with Swords, Clubs, and other miſchievous Inſtruments, that he fell down upon the place as Dead, but they finding him yet to breath, they halled him to Priſon where he Dyed.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> hearing of theſe Stirs as he ſate at Dinner, left his Company, and haſted towards the Multitude, where being Arrived, he admoniſhed them by many perſwaſive Arguments to ceaſe from ſuch Rebellious proceedings and to depart to their reſpective homes, affirming, that he wonld bring all things that had been done to their prejudice to an amica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compoſure, upon theſe perſwaſions of the Biſhop, every one returned to their Habitations, ſo that all the Multitude were diſperſed in leſs then three hours, yet their hatred againſt the Duke could not be ſo thoroughly oblitered, but that the ſame day they hung up his Arms reverſe in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Streets of the City, in token of his being a Traytor to the Kingdom, (as they then Related) thereby to caſt an odium upon his Name, the which when the Duke heard, he requeſted the Biſhop to Pronounce Sentence of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the doers thereof, the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> therefore being aſſiſted by the Aldermen and other of the prime Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, did pronounce the aforeſaid Sentence, the Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> being unwilling to Incurr the Peoples hate thereby, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it.</p>
            <p>Within three or four days after the Duke went to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament Houſe, where he and ſeveral of the Lords that were his Friends being Seated, they demanded of the Knights and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes to return an anſwer to what had been formerly propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as to the Subſidie; and had return made by the Knights Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54234:8"/> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they would not help their Soveraign Lord the King with one penny a head only, but with a groat for every Head throughout the Kingdom above 14 years of Age, if ſo be that Mony might be depoſited in the Hands of certain Lords and Barrons, till ſuch time occaſion required the diſpoſure of the ſame, in the mannagement of the Kings affairs, and that every Religious Perſon promoted ſhould pay one Shilling.</p>
            <p>The Duke having thus obtained his deſire, in this point began to call to mind the affront offered to him by the <hi>Londoners,</hi> wherefore he cauſed the King to ſend for the Mayor, Sheriffs, and Aldermen of the City, who being Introduced into the Kings preſence (he being at his mannor of <hi>Sheene</hi> now <hi>Richmond</hi>) they found him placed in a Chair, not well able to Speak, by reaſon of his Sickneſs, the Duke, the Arch-Biſhop, and other Biſhops, with many Lords and Honourable Perſonages ſitting about him, where after due Reverence made, and Silence commanded, Sir <hi>Robert Aſton</hi> began an Oration, <hi>perſwading the Citizens to confeſs their great and Heinous offences againſt the King and Duke, and to ſubmit themſelves to their Mercy;</hi> whereunto the <hi>Londoners</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>that they had not conſpired againſt the Duke; neither had there heen any Evildone or ſpoken againſt him, which they did conſent to or know off,</hi> which they were ready to prove before their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord the King and Duke himſelf; yet they confeſſed that they could not ſtay the Inſolency of the unruly Multitude, by whom that which had chanced was committed, wherefore they requeſted the King that he would not by any means Punniſh thoſe that were Innocent and Ignorant of the Fact, inſtead of thoſe that committed it, promiſing that they would do their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavour to apprehend ſuch as were guilty, and compell them by Law to make ſatisfaction, ſaying, <hi>that they were no able to do in that point for the Duke as they would,</hi> whereupon they were diſmiſſed, not a little glad that they came off ſo well.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54234:8"/>
            <p>A while after the King ſent privately to them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, That they ſhould Aſſemble together, and make a Wax Candle or Taper, with the Dukes Arms on it, and carry it in a General Proceſſion, to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, there continually to burn before the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> at the Charges of the City. This was exactly performed; but when the Duke came to hear of it, it rather Exaſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated him, then any ways gave him Satisfaction; wherefore he threatned the Citizens more than formerly, ſaying; that it rather redounded to his diſgrace than Honour; for that during his Life, and in a time of Health, they had offered up his Arms: But they excuſed themſelves, by alledging, it was done at the Commandment of the King his Father, and that they would have done any thing that might have pleaſed him. But this would not avail them, for the Duke ceaſed not till he had diſplaced <hi>Adam Staple,</hi> Mayor of the City, and obtained <hi>Nicholas Brember</hi> to be Elected in his room; and on the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 1377. cauſed him to take his Oath at the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> as likewiſe ſeveral Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were Outed, and others placed in their ſteads.</p>
            <p>And thus have I given the Reader an Impartial Relation of what happened to the Citizens and City of <hi>London,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, who Dyed at <hi>Richmond</hi> Anno. 1377. In the 65 Year of his Age, having Reigned 50 Years, 4 Months, and 6 Days.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall proceed to relate what happened to the City during the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, Son to the Black Prince, and Grand-Son to the beforementioned King. But before I Treat of the Diſcord that happened, I do not think it amiſs (though indeed it may be counted by ſome a Digreſſion) to inform the Reader, how at the beginning of this Kings Reign the Citizens were Reconciled to their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Enemy, the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> was no ſooner departed this Life, but the City ſent ſeveral of the Chief Citizens to wait upon <hi>Richard</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54234:9"/> at <hi>Kinington,</hi> where he and the Princeſs his Mother remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to promiſe him their ready Obedience, in Proclaiming him King, as his Right by Confirmation of Parliament, and the Eſtabliſhed Laws of the Kingdom; and to aſſure him of their Loyalty and conſtant Fidelity, Humbly beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, That he would take upon him to end the diſcord between them and his Uncle the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh which, he promiſed to uſe his utmoſt endeavour, and with many thanks, ſuffered the Citizens to depart to their reſpective Habitations.</p>
            <p>The morrow after, there were ſent into <hi>London</hi> from the King, the Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> Sir <hi>Nicholas Bond,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Adderbury,</hi> to give them a farther Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Kings affection towards them; and how that he had ſpoken to the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> in their behalfs, and that he had ſubmitted himſelf in all things to the King, touching their Cauſe; and that it was the Kings pleaſure they ſhould do the like; and then he would do his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that an Honourable Agreement might be made on the behalf of the City.</p>
            <p>When the Citizens heard this Meſſage, they were not well pleaſed, by reaſon they knew that the King being young, muſt do what was done by Subſtitutes; and that the Duke being powerful at Court, would not miſs of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing favour; yet notwithſtanding, they promiſed to ſubmit themſelves; if ſo be the afore-mentioned Knights would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake upon their Oath of Fidelity and Knighthood, that they ſhould not ſuffer either in Body or Goods; which they conſenting to, the Chief Citizens went with them to <hi>Sheene</hi> where the young King was, with his Mother, the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and a great number of Nobility; when the King knew they were come, he cauſed them to be brought before him, and in the full Aſſembly ſo handled the matter, that the Duke and they entred into an intire Amity, and perpetual Friendſhip; and after that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54234:9"/> the Duke behaved himſelf ſo Courteouſly towards the Common people, that all their former hatred was turned into Love and Good-will towards him: And ſo much of the Citizens Reconciliation with the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and now to my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>15th</hi> Year of the Reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Anno. 1392. the Parliament then Sitting, and not having concluded upon any ſpeedy way of raiſing money; the King, to ſupply his preſent Occaſions, ſent to the City to borrow the Summ of a 1000 pounds, the which they not only uncourteouſly refuſed to lend him, but likewiſe beat and grievouſly wounded a <hi>Lumbard</hi> who offered to ſupply him with the like Summ; of which the King being adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, was greately diſpleaſed with the Citizens; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon calling together moſt of the Peers and Noble men of his Kingdom, he complained to them of the froward deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Londoners,</hi> and deſired them to take notice of the Affront they had put upon him. When the King had told them his mind, the Lords, after a ſhort Conference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the matter, gave Counſel, <hi>That it was not only Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, but very requiſite, that the Inſolent Pride of thoſe preſumptious Perſons ſhould be ſpeedily Repreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Citizens of <hi>London</hi> (as it appeareth in thoſe days) uſing their Authority to the utmoſt, had deviſed and ſet forth divers Orders and Conſtitutions, to abridge the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of Forreigners that came to the City to utter their Wares; which likewiſe cauſed great Complaints againſt them: They in many particulars, as ſome Writers affirm, having ſtretched beyond their Bounds, all which ſerved but as Fuel to increaſe the Kings diſpleaſure againſt them.</p>
            <p>And now becauſe I will omit nothing that may occaſion any Objection; It is not amiſs to give the Reader another Relation, though different from the former, how the City fell into the Kings diſpleaſure, though it was Written by an unknown Author, and therefore of what Credit, I muſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54234:10"/> leave to the judgement of the Reader, many having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected it as Fabulous, and affirm, that what is before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned was the real occaſion, that which was pretended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> That one of the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s Servants meeting a Bakers Boy in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> took out of his Basket a Loaf, and utterly refuſed to reſtore it again; for which, when the Boy became Clamorous, he broke his head, and gave him many blows upon his body, which the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants perceiving, they came together and would have taken the Biſhops man, in order to have conveyed him to Priſon, but that his Fellow-Servants hearing in what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he was, came to his Reſcue, and carried him by force into the Biſhops houſe, which was at that time in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet:</hi> whereupon the multitude increaſing, they threatned to pull down the houſe unleſs the Offender was delivered up, and had effected it, had not the Mayor and Sheriffs with conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Halberts, come in time to appeaſe them and oblige them to depart every man to his own Houſe. And that of this the Biſhop being advertized, made his Complaint to the King; and for that cauſe, ſays this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Author, was it that the Citizens fell into the Kings diſpleaſure: but by this his concluſion it proved fictitious; for he tells us, that the Cities Charter upon that cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, it was reſtored by the Interceſſion of <hi>Richard Gravesend,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi> In acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which, the Citizens for a long time after repaired once a year to his Grave in the Middle Iſle of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But that is utterly falſe, for at that time <hi>Robert Braybrook</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> the aforeſaid <hi>Graveſend</hi> having been Biſhop in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, Anno. 1303. almoſt 90 years before this time, after whom ſucceeded him in the Biſhoprick, <hi>Ralph Baldock, Gilbert Seagrave, Richard Newport, Stephen Graveſend, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Went worth, Ralph Stratford, Michael Norbrook, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sudbury, William Courtney,</hi> and <hi>Robert Braybrook,</hi> who ſate Biſhop 1381, until the year 1403.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:54234:10"/>
            <p>Moreover, The place of Burial in St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> whereunto the Mayor and Citizens of <hi>London</hi> were wont to repair, was of <hi>William,</hi> who ſat Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in the time of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conqueror, and of him purchaſed the Charter of the ſaid City. Having thus, as I think, cleared all Objections that might have been ſtarted as to the beginning of the Feud, I ſhall proceed to relate what happened e're the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens could appeaſe the Kings Anger.</p>
            <p>After the Lords had given their opinions as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, the King commanded that the Mayor, Sheriffs, and ſeveral of the moſt wealthy Citizens, ſhould be Arreſted and brought to <hi>Nottingham,</hi> where on the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> in the year aforeſaid, <hi>John Hind</hi> the Mayor was Depoſed and ſent to <hi>Windſor</hi>-Caſtle, as likewiſe the Sheriffs; one of them being ſent to <hi>Wallingford</hi>-Caſtle, and the other to <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>-Caſtle, and the other Citizens to ſeveral adjacent Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, there to continue till ſuch time as the King with his Councel ſhould determine, what ſhould be done in that Affair.</p>
            <p>The Council had not long conſulted about it, before they Unanimouſly conſented, and determined that from thenceforth the <hi>Londoners</hi> ſhould not chuſe nor have any Mayor, but that the King ſhould appoint one of his Knights to Govern the City immediately under him; and that their Priviledges ſhould be Revoked, their Liberties Diſanull'd, and their Laws Abrogated, all which was accordingly done, the King immediately appointing for Warden or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Sir <hi>Edward Darlingrug,</hi> Impowering him not only to Rule the City, but to ſee the Adminiſtration of Juſtice done in all Caſes, being ſtiled Lord Warden of the City, and ſo continued for the ſpace of Ten days: When the King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the City, it being the 1 of <hi>July,</hi> in the <hi>16th</hi> year of his Reign, he diſcharged him of the ſaid Office, and placed in his ſtead one Sir <hi>Baldwin Radington,</hi> a right Circumſpect and Diſcreet Gentleman, who knew how not only to pleaſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54234:11"/> the Kings mind, but alſo to retain the good Will of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, by putting them in hopes of the Kings Favour, and in time to regain what, by their unadvized raſhneſs, they had loſt, as in the end it happened.</p>
            <p>For at the Inceſſant Intreaties and unwearied Endeavours of ſeveral Noble Perſons, and eſpecially the Duke of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> the King began to relent and hearken to the offered Submiſſion of the Citizens, fully determining with himſelf to abate of the Rigor lately impoſed, eſpecially when he call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to mind the Honour and Service they had formerly done him, upon ſeveral accounts, and the great Gifts they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him; whereupon he ſent for divers of the Chief Citizens to come to him, he then keeping his Court at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> to ſhew by what Charters and Grants they held their Liberty, Priviledges, and peculiar Laws, as well the new as the old, that ſo he might determine by the Advice of his Council, which ſhould be reſtored, and which abrogated. Hereupon when the ſaid Liberties and Priviledges were laid forth to the view of ſuch Perſons as were appointed by the King to take them into conſideration; after a due Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome were Ratified and Tollerated, and others utterly Abrogated and taken away.</p>
            <p>Neither could they for the preſent recover the Perſon or Dignity of their Mayor, nor obtain the Kings intire favour, till they had ſatisfied the Damages and Injury by them done, either to the King or his People; and whereas the King had been at great Charges in preparing Forces to Chaſtize them, as he had abſolutely determined, had they not ſubmitted themſelves to his mercy, ſuch Charges as he had been at were expected to be payed by the City; the Citizens therefore went, and in a moſt Humble manner tendered again their Submiſſion, offering, as a Recompence and Satisfaction of their Treſpaſſes, 10000 pounds (a great Summ in thoſe days) but they were at that time ſent home, and a certain day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for their appearance, not being given in the leaſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54234:11"/> to underſtand what they muſt pay, till the King had adviſed with his Council about the matter; at length, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Nobility, the King was content to pardon all Offences paſt, but firſt the Citizens were told that the King intended to come from his Mannor of <hi>Sheene</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> and then undoubtedly upon knowledge had of their good meaning and Loyal Intentions for the future, they ſhould obtain his favour.</p>
            <p>The Citizens having received this welcome news, did not only prepare themſelves to meet him, and preſent him with Gifts of great value, but alſo to adorn, deck, and trim their City with ſumptuous Pageants, rich Hangings, and gorgeous Furniture in all points, as they were wont at a Coronation. At the day appointed 3 or 400 of the chief Citizens on Horſe-back all in their Liverys, preſented themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him upon the Heath on this ſide <hi>Sheene,</hi> and in humble wiſe craved pardon (in the name of all the Citizens) for their paſt Offences, and beſought him to take his way to his Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> through the City of <hi>London;</hi> which requeſt the King granted, and ſo held on his Journey till he came to <hi>London-bridge,</hi> where he was preſented with a fair White Steed, Saddled, Bridled, and traped in Cloth of Gold, parted with Red and White: As likewiſe to the Queen was given, a White Palfrey, Saddled, Bridled, and traped as the former; both which were thankfully accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo both the King and Queen paſſing forwards, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the City, prepared for their Reception, as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited; and over and above, all the ſubſtantial Citizens ſtanding on both ſides the Streets, and as the King approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with audible voice cry'd; King <hi>Richard,</hi> King <hi>Richard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Standard in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> was a right ſumptuous Stage ordained, on which was placed divers Repreſentations, and amongſt the reſt, one Dreſſed like an Angel, who hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Crown of Gold in his hand, richly ſet-with Stones, put it upon the Kings head as he paſſed by; as likewiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54234:12"/> on the Queens; this done, the King Rode to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, and there making his Offering, took Horſe again, and Rode to his Pallace at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the Mayor and Aldermen take their leave of him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Morrow the Mayor and his Brethren went again to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there being admitted to the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, preſented him with two Guilt Baſons, and in them 2000 Nobles in Gold, beſeeching him to be a good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord to the poor diſtreſſed City. Theſe Preſents he received in Courteous manner, and gave them words of Comfort, promiſing to endeavour the forgetting their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; ſo that three days after they received a new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all their old Liberties, (at leaſt ſuch as were moſt advantageous to the City, and no Detriment to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners) wherefore the Citizens being not a little pleaſed, after ſome Conſideration had, they made a <hi>Tablet</hi> for an Altar, all of Silver, Guilt with Gold, in which was curiouſly Ingraven the Story of St. <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, it being eſteemed to be worth 1000 Marks; This they preſented to the King, which he ſhortly after offered to the Shrine of St. <hi>Edward.</hi> The <hi>Londoners</hi> believed, that by theſe Gifts they had ſo far Ingratiated themſelves into the Kings favour, as to be out of all danger, and that no farther trouble could accrue; notwithſtanding which, they were compelled to give the King after all this, the Summ of 10000 pounds, which was raiſed by a general Collection amongſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who payed it with great Regret and Grudging.</p>
            <p>Hitherto Reader, I have given you an account what has happened to the City of <hi>London,</hi> and what means have been uſed by the Mayor, Aldermen, and other Citizens, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the Anger of ſuch Princes, into whoſe diſpleaſure they had fallen; yet to give a greater Confirmation to the truth of what happened in the Reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, I ſhall give another Relation of the ſeveral Tranſactions, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54234:12"/> it was taken out of the Canon of <hi>Licester</hi> Abby, by <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Knighton:</hi> In the year (ſays he) 1392. the King called a great Council at <hi>Stamford,</hi> on the morrow after <hi>Trinity</hi> Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, about certain Affairs concerning the <hi>French-men,</hi> in which Council he aſſembled together his chief Officers, and invited all the old Souldiers that ſerved in former Wars, to repair to him, that ſo he might be the better enabled to put in practice what ſhould be adviſed and concluded on; the King alſo held a great Council at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> at the Feaſt of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> where he cauſed the Mayor of <hi>London</hi> with the four and twenty Aldermen, the two Sheriffs, and, four and twenty Commoners of the moſt principal and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy amongſt them, to be brought before him, where he Charged them, That they had forfeited a Bond of 9000 pounds to him, beſides their Liberties and Priviledges; which Bond or Obligation they had formerly made to the King, as a Confirmation of their Obedience; and after the King had declared what new offences they had Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he diſcharged the Mayor, two Sheriffs, and the reſt of the Officers of their reſpective Offices, and ſent the Mayor and the two Sheriffs to a certain place, there to be kept in Cuſtody as his Priſoners, diveſting the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> of all her Honours and Priviledges, inſomuch that a Citizen or Free-man ſhould have no more Prerogative than a Forreigner or Stranger; He alſo appointed the Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leridge</hi> to be Governour thereof, to keep and ſee kept, the Kings Laws, and his Leige-people within the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in due order, until ſuch time as the King had otherwiſe provided for them; after which, a day was ſet them to anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the King and his Council to certain Interrogatorys, which was on the Feaſt of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and the place affixed for that purpoſe, was <hi>VVindſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean while, through the Mediation of ſuch as were well-willers to the City, the Kings Indignation was ſomewhat mittigated and pacified towards them, inſomuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54234:13"/> that at length he releaſed the Mayor and Sheriffs from their Confinements, ſending them home to their reſpective houſes, ſetting over the City (notwithſtanding) a new Keeper, or Governour, reſerving all the Priviledges and Liberties in his own hands: In the mean time, the Citizens conſulting what was beſt to be done, they at laſt agreed to ſubmit themſelves and all their Goods, to the Kings mercy; when upon the Aſſumption of the bleſſed Virgin, all the Wealthy Citizens came to the King, and ſubmitted themſelves accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; inſomuch that he ſpeak friendly to them, and began to receive them into favour: On the <hi>VVedneſday</hi> enſuing, the King was purpoſed to come to <hi>London,</hi> and the Citizens in great numbers came out to meet him on Horſe-back, and ſuch as could not procure Horſes, went on foot to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, which they performed with Shouts and joyful Acclamations; and not only men, but likewiſe women and Children, came flocking about him: When he came near the City, the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> with all the Clergy and Religious Perſons of all Degrees whatſoever, went out to meet him, ſo that in that Proceſſion, there were ſaid to be above 500 Boys in Surplices; moreover, the Citizens trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the out-ſide of their houſes and Chambers in every ſtreet, through which the King and Queen were to paſs; as for the Houſes of the wealthier ſort, they were bravely garniſhed with Cloth of Gold, Silver, Velvet, and other Rich and ſumptuous Stuffs: In <hi>Cheapſide</hi> there was a Conduit, out of which two Spouts ran with red and white Wines, and upon the <hi>Conduit</hi> ſtood a little Boy, Appareled like an Angel, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Golden Cup in his hand, in which he preſented Wine to the King and Queen as they paſſed by; In the mean time, ſeveral Citizens preſented the King with a Crown of Gold, of great value, as likewiſe another to the Queen; and a while after they preſented her with a Tablet of Gold with the Story of St. <hi>Ann</hi> Ingraven in it, the which ſhe moſt greatfully accepted, and the rather, by reaſon her own name
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54234:13"/> was <hi>Ann; (as ſaith our Hiſtorian)</hi> As likewiſe to the King, a Golden Tablet of the bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> to the value of 800 pounds; ſuch, ſo great and wondeful Honours, did the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> to the King and Queen, as the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had been never done to any King or Queen of this Realm; and ſo going forwards, they brought the King and Queen to <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> where the King placing himſelf upon his Throne, and all his Nobles ſtanding about him, one, in the Kings behalf, as his Speaker, gave the Citizens thanks for the great Honour they had done him, and the Princely Preſents which they had beſtowed upon him; and then they being commanded every man to fall to his buſineſs, and that in the next Parliament they ſhould have their final Anſwer, they departed with great joy: And thus far this Author makes his Report of what happened upon the afore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned occaſion.</p>
            <p>After this Reconciliation, by the means and methods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recited, the Citizens followed their Imployments peaceably, having ſeveral Grants and ſmunities added to the former; as alſo, when King <hi>Richard</hi> was Depoſed by <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Son to <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> the Citizens, by ſiding with the Conqueror, preſerved their Charter and Liberties; as likewiſe, during his Reign, who took the Rule of the Kingdom upon him, by the Name of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> After him ſucceeded his Son, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, into whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Citizens highly Ingratiated themſelves, dealing likewiſe faithfully with his Son, <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, till ſuch time as <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth became Conqueror; at which time they neglected him, as thinking it ſafeſt to ſail with the Wind of Power: During his Reign, they continued peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, having many of their former Charters and Grants confirmed, though not without conſiderable ſumms of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on the parts of the City.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, being a Uſurper, was obliged to make the Citizens his Friends, for the better ſupport
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54234:14"/> of his Dignity; ſo that they lived quietly during his Reign, as alſo, during the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh; but in the Ninth year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, theſe following Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances happened.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>London</hi> being greatly Infeſted with Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who notwithſtanding, the Priviledges and Charters granted, did uſe all manner of Handicrafts, and had ſuch Licenſes to vend their Manufactures, that the Citizens were greatly Impoveriſhed; nor was that all, for they being Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened by relying upon the favour of the Courtiers, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly abuſed the Citizens, not only with reproachful words, but likewiſe by Stroaks; and amongſt the reſt, one <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis D'Bard</hi> a <hi>Lumbard,</hi> cauſing a Citizens Wife to convey her Husbands Plate and other Goods, to his houſe, he there kept her, and would by no means reſtore her, although an Action was brought againſt him.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch like matters, ſtirred up the Citizens Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt the Strangers; but above all, one <hi>John Lincoln</hi> a <hi>Broaker,</hi> who having drawn up a Bill of Grievances, with it he went to Dr. <hi>Standiſh,</hi> and deſired him to read it in his Pulpit at the <hi>Spittle,</hi> (he being to Preach there on the <hi>Munday</hi> in <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Week;) but he like a Wiſe Man, and good Subject, conſidering of what evil conſequence it might prove, refuſed it; upon which, <hi>Lincoln</hi> went to Dr. <hi>Bele,</hi> who was to Preach there on the <hi>Tueſday,</hi> and ſo prevailed with him, that he openly read it, the Contents being theſe.</p>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>The Subſtance of the Bill of Complaint, Read by Dr. <hi>Bele,</hi> at the <hi>SPITTLE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TO all you, the VVorſhipful Lords and Maſters of this City, that will take Compaſſion on the poor People, your Neighbours; as alſo, of the great and inſufferable Hurts, Loſſes, and Hindrances, whereof proceedeth the extream pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to all the Kings Subjects that inhabit within this City and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54234:14"/> the Suburbs thereof; for ſo it is, that the</hi> Aliens <hi>and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers eat the Bread from the Fatherleſs Children, and take the Living from the Artificers, and the Intercourſe from all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, whereby Poverty is ſo increaſed, that every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waileth the Miſery of the other; for Crafts-men be brought to Beggery, and Merchants to Needineſs; wherefore the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes conſidered, the Redreſs muſt be of the Commons, knit and united to one part; and as the hurt and dammages grieveth all men, that they ſet their willing power for the Remedy, and not to ſuffer the ſaid</hi> Aliens <hi>ſo highly in their Wealth, and the Natural born men of this Kingdom to come to Poverty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this Letter or Bill, there was more, but the Dr. would read no farther, finding it greatly tended to Sedition, by ſtirring up and exaſperating the hot-headed multitude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Strangers, yet he took a Text to the purpoſe, <hi>viz. The Heaven of Heavens is the Lords, but the Earth hath he given to the Sons of Men.</hi> And thereupon went on to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the people to ſtand up for their Callings and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, inſinuating the Lawfulneſs of fighting for, and defending what was their Right, ſaying; That <hi>the Birds defended their Neſts with their Bills and Claws;</hi> as alſo, <hi>the wild Beaſts of the Forrests their Dens.</hi> This, and ſome other occaſions of offence, that miniſtered themſelves ſo inflamed, the Youths and a certain company of Deboiſt perſons, who hoped for Plunder if it came to a Tumultuous Inſurrection, that on the <hi>28th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> they gathered together in ſmall Companies, and quarrel'd with ſuch Strangers as they met in the Streets, beating and throwing them in the Kennels; inſomuch that notice being given, the Lord Mayor ſent and apprehended the chief Authors of ſuch Incivilities; <hi>viz. Stephen Studly</hi> a Skinner, <hi>Bets, Stevenſon,</hi> and divers others, who were impriſoned: Whereupon a Rumor (without any certain Author) was ſpread, That on the <hi>May-day</hi> following, the <hi>City</hi> would Riſe &amp; ſlay all the <hi>Aliens;</hi> of which, the Kings
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54234:15"/> Council having notice, they ſent for the Lord Mayor and ſome of the Aldermen, telling them what had been report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, adviſing them to look well to the City, and be in a readineſs to ſuppreſs any Riotous Aſſembly, which they promiſed to do, and ſo departed.</p>
               <p>Being arrived at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> the Mayor Aſſembled the Court of Aldermen to conſider what courſe was moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to be taken; and after many debates, concluded that every Alderman ſhould take charge of his reſpective Ward; and that notice ſhould immediately be given to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Maſter, to keep in their Servants till Nine of the Clock the next morning, upon pain of his being impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if he were found abroad, and ſo they broke up.</p>
               <p>After this Commandment, in the Evening as Sir <hi>John Mundie</hi> (one of the Aldermen) was going home, he found two young men in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> playing at Cudgels, and a great company ſtanding about them, whereupon he, in the Kings Name, commanded them to depart to their reſpective homes, but they refuſing, he ordered one of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute to be carryed to the <hi>Compter;</hi> whereupon his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows came to his Reſcue, crying, <hi>Out Prentices and Clubs;</hi> whereupon the doors flew open on every ſide, and out came a number of Armed Youths, who altogether ſetting up a cry, a great multitude gathered, inſomuch that the Alderman and his followers, were forced to flye, for by Eleven of the Clock that Evening, there were no leſs then ſeven hundred gathered in a company of all ſorts, by whoſe Shouting they ſtill increaſed, there coming at leaſt 300 more out of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, who had no ſooner joyned them, but they went and broke up the <hi>Compters,</hi> releaſing not only thoſe that were in Cuſtody of their own gang, but likewiſe a conſiderable number of other Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and from thence they went to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring by force, they delivered the reſt of their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without any regard to the Lord Mayor and Sheriffs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54234:15"/> who were come thither, and made Proclamation in the Kings Name, that every one ſhould depart to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective homes.</p>
               <p>Then away they went to St. <hi>Martins-Le-Grand,</hi> which at that time was Inhabited for the moſt part, by Strangers, where they were met by Sir <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> and others, who advized them to deſiſt, but nothing was obeyed, for whilſt he was Treating with them, the Strangers threw Stones, Bats, and ſcalding Water, out of their Windows; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſeveral honeſt Perſons were hurt, and amongſt the reſt, one <hi>Nicholas Downs,</hi> a Serjeant at Arms, who in a fury cry'd, Down with 'um; whereupon the Rabble broke up the doors, and ſpoiled about 20 Houſes, not diſcerning between the Goods of <hi>Aliens</hi> and Natives.</p>
               <p>From thence they went to <hi>Cornhill,</hi> where they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the like Outrages upon the Houſes of <hi>French-men, Lumbards,</hi> and others, that dwelt within the Gate of one Mr. <hi>Mutas,</hi> called <hi>Green-Gate;</hi> this Man being by Birth a <hi>Pickard,</hi> and a great promoter of the Forraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Trade and Manufacturies in <hi>England,</hi> for which he had (paſt doubt) been ſlain, had he fallen into the hands of the Rabble; but finding him not, they Riffled his Houſe, and carried thence, things of great price: And thus they continued to range from place to place till Eleven a Clock the next day, which was the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> but by Three of the Clock they were many of them diſperſed; upon which, the Watches of the City being in a readineſs, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them were Apprehended and committed Priſoners to the <hi>Tower, Compters,</hi> and <hi>Newgate;</hi> but they were for the moſt part the young Fry, the Knaves that had ſet them on, (with ſuch Rich Bootys as they deſired,) timely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing themſelves.</p>
               <p>About 5 of the Clock, the Earls of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> and <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Thomas Dokercie,</hi> Lord of St. <hi>Johns,</hi> and <hi>George Nevill,</hi> Lord of <hi>Avergavenny,</hi> with their Attendants, came into the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54234:16"/> City, having at leaſt 600 Men in their company, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fear of their approach or otherwiſe, the Rioters were all diſperſed, yet ſome of the Priſoners were brought before them in the <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and Examined; as alſo Dr. <hi>Bele,</hi> for the Seditious Sermon he Preached, upon which he was committed Priſoner to the <hi>Tower.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A while after the King iſſued out a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> for the Tryal of the Offenders, directed to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and divers other Lords; as alſo to the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, Juſtices, and others; ſo that the Duke came into the City, attended by 1300 Men in Arms, and in the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Examined the matter: yet upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination it did not appear that there had been any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Meetings, but that it happened rather by chance, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs what <hi>Lincoln</hi> had done therein, by ſtirring up the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hatred againſt Strangers.</p>
               <p>After this they went to the Houſe of the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Fineux,</hi> Seituate in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> there to adjudge and determine the matter; where, when the Judges and the Kings Council had well conſidered the Statute <hi>Anno Tertio</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, in Relation to the Breach of Leagues which they ſaid was manifeſtly done by the abuſe offered to Merchants, Strangers, and Reteiners to Forreign Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors; they concluded that all Perſons who were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the Inſurrection, aiding, abetting, or encouraging the ſame, were Guilty of High-Treaſon.</p>
               <p>The buſineſs being brought to this paſs, they Adjourned to <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> where on the <hi>2d.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> the Offenders were brought before them and Indicted, as well for the Inſurrection, as the ſeveral Robberies that were Committed during the Uproar, to which they pleaded <hi>Not Guilty;</hi> a great many of them not exceeding 14 years of Age, yet were there amongſt them, Laborours, Husband-men, and others, that were not of the City, the whole number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to 278 Perſons; amongſt whom was <hi>John Lincoln,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:54234:16"/> who was Indicted as the principal Contriver of the ſaid Inſurrection, to which he pleaded <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> and had three days given him to prepare for his defence; ſo that for that day there were no farther Proceedings; but upon the day affixed, the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Surry,</hi> came again, attended with 2000 Armed men, who kept the Streets, and the Priſoners being brought, upon their Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, 13 were found Guilty, and adjudged to be Hanged; whereupon Eleven pair of Gallows were ſet up in divers parts of the City; when at the day appointed for Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, the Priſoners were brought forth with Ropes about their Necks and Arms, and in the preſence of the Lord <hi>Edmund,</hi> Son to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> (to whom the charge of ſeeing it done was committed) they were Executed without any reſpect to their Youth.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>17th</hi> of <hi>May, Lincoln, Sherwin,</hi> and the two <hi>Bettſes,</hi> being Brothers, with ſeveral of their Confederates, were found Guilty, and received Sentence as the former; when within a ſhort time after, they were drawn upon Hurdles to the Standard in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> where <hi>Lincoln</hi> was firſt Executed, but as the reſt were about to be turn'd off, a Reprieve came from the King to ſtay Execution; upon which the people Shouted, crying, <hi>God Save the King;</hi> and thereupon the Priſoners were carryed back to Priſon, there to attend the Kings farther pleaſure.</p>
               <p>After this, all the Armed Men which before had kept Watch in the City, were withdrawn, which gave the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens hope that the Kings diſpleaſure towards them was not ſo great as themſelves conceived; whereupon on the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> the King Riding at his Mannor of <hi>Greenwich,</hi> the Mayor, Recorder, and divers Aldermen, went in Mourning Gowns to wait upon him; and having admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the <hi>Privy-Chamber</hi> door; and after they had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended there for ſome time, the King, attended with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Nobles, came forth; whereupon they falling
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54234:17"/> upon their Knees, the Recorder in the Name of the reſt, ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt Natural, Benign, and our Soveraign Lord, we well know that your Grace is highly diſpleaſed with us of your City of</hi> London, <hi>for the great Riot done and Committed there; wherefore we aſſure your Grace, that none of us, nor no Honeſt Perſon, were condeſcending to that Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; yet we, our Wives and Children, every hour lament that your Favour ſhould be taken from us; and foraſmuch as Light and Idle Perſons were the doers of the ſame, we moſt humbly beſeech your Grace to have Mercy on us, for our negligence and compaſſion on the Offenders for their Offences and Treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which the King Replyed; <hi>Truly you have highly diſpleaſed and offended us, and therefore you ought to wail and be ſorry for the ſame; and whereas you ſay that</hi> you the Subſtantial Citizens were not conſenting to what happened, <hi>it appeareth to the contrary; for you never moved to let them, nor ſtirred to fight with thoſe whom you ſay were ſo ſmall a number of light perſons; wherefore we muſt think, and you cannot deny, but that you did wink at the matter; therefore at this time, we will neither grant you our Favour nor Good-will, nor to the Offenders mercy, but reſort to our Lord</hi> Chancellor, <hi>and he ſhall make you an Anſwer, and declare to you our pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this Speech of the Kings, the Citizens departed very ſorrowful, but having notice that the King intended to be at his Pallace of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> on the <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> they reſolved to repair thither, which they did according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though not without the appointment of Cardinal <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> who was then Lord <hi>Chancellor;</hi> when as a Cloth of Eſtate being placed at the upper-end of <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> the King took his place, and after him the Cardinal, the Dukes of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Wilt-ſhire, Surry, Shrewsbury,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> with ſeveral others, the Lord Mayor,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54234:17"/> Recorder, and Aldermen, together with many of the Commons, attending in their Liveries; when about Nine of the Clock, order was given for the bringing forth the Priſoners, which was accordingly done; ſo that in they came in their Shirts, bound together with Ropes, and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters about their Necks, to the number of 400 Men and Eleven Women, one after another, which fight ſo moved ſeveral of the Nobility, that they became earneſt Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors to the King for their pardon.</p>
               <p>When ſilence was made, and they were all come into the Kings preſence, the Cardinal ſharply Rebuked the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty, for their Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and then addreſſing his Speech to the Priſoners, he told them, That for their Offences againſt the Laws of the Realm, and againſt his Majeſties Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, they had deſerved Death; whereupon they all ſet up a piteous cry, ſaying; <hi>Mercy Gracious Lord, Mercy;</hi> which ſo moved the King, that at the earneſt Intreaty of the Lords, he pronounced them pardoned; upon which, giving a great Shout, they threw up their Halters towards the Roof of the Hall, crying, <hi>God Save the King:</hi> When this News was bruited abroad, ſeveral that had been in the Inſurrection and had eſcaped, came in upon their own accords with Ropes about their Necks, and received the benefit of the Kings pardon; after which the Cardinal gave them ſeveral good Exhortations, tending to Loyalty and Obedience, and ſo diſmiſſed them, to their no ſmall joy; and within a while after, the Gallowſes that were ſet in the ſeveral parts of the City, were taken down, which ſo far pleaſed the Citizens, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed infinite thanks to the King for his Clemency.</p>
               <p>This Company was called the <hi>Black VVaggon,</hi> and the day whereon this Riot and Inſurrection hapned, bears the name of <hi>Ill-May-day</hi> to theſe our preſent times. And thus, have you heard how the Citizens eſcaped the Kings diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54234:18"/> and were again received into favour; though, as it is thought, not without paying a conſiderable Summ of Money to the Cardinal to ſtand their Friend, for at that time he was in ſuch Power, that he did all with the King.</p>
               <p>This Broil being over, the Citizens lived in Peace all the days of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, lending him at divers times, great Summs of Money to carry on his Wars againſt <hi>France,</hi> and upon other occaſions.</p>
               <p>During the Reign of his Son King <hi>Edward,</hi> likewiſe, all things were preſerved peaceably within the City, a good Underſtanding being for the moſt part between them and their Prince, inſomuch that the City greatly flouriſhed under his Pious Goverment, he giving to them his Pallace of <hi>Bridewell, Chriſt's-Hoſpital,</hi> St. <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mews Hoſpital,</hi> and that of <hi>Bethelem,</hi> with an <hi>Annual</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue for the relief of the Poor; together with ſeveral Grants, Priviledges, and Immunities; ſo that to gratifie him, they conſented to the Eſtabliſhing the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> his Couzen, in the Succeſſion, and after his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe were aſſiſting at her Coronation, promiſing to ſtand by her with their Lives and Fortunes, although within a ſhort time after, they left her to the mercy of her mercileſs Enemy Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> by that means think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to appeaſe her for the wrong they had done, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring her <hi>Illegitimate;</hi> but that availed not, for ſhe was never throughly Reconciled to the Citizens during the whole courſe of her Reign, by reaſon of the Affronts they frequently offered, and the Revolt of 600 of them from the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> to <hi>Wyate,</hi> upon the Dukes approach to <hi>Rocheſter;</hi> ſo that ſhe ſtill kept an Eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the City, and often determined with her ſelf, to take away, or abridge the Charter; and for that purpoſe, conſulted with her Council, and had proceeded therein, had not her death prevented it.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54234:18"/>
               <p>When her Glorious Siſter, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> came to the Crown, ſhe greatly Honoured the City, and was as intirely beloved of all the Citizens, unleſs a few Factious perſons, who were ſcattered here and there, whom by wholſom Laws, ſhe endeavoured to reſtrain, they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe aſpiring to an unparalel'd height of Inſolency.</p>
               <p>After her death, King <hi>James</hi> of ever Bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, Uniting the Crowns of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> was moſt joyfull received by the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> and much augmented their Priviledges, freely confirming their Charter, which they delivered up to his Majeſty for that purpoſe, and continued during his moſt Chriſtian Reign, in great Proſperity and Peace.</p>
               <p>But in the fourth year of his Son, <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of ever bleſſed Memory, Anno. 1628. on the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> this following Diſturbance happened; One Dr. <hi>Lamb</hi> (by ſome reputed to a <hi>Necromancer,</hi> though many were, and are to this day, of a contrary opinion) comeing through <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> where being eſpyed by ſome Ill-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons, who envyed his great parts, they cryed out, D. <hi>Lamb,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lamb;</hi> whereupon a great number of Lewd Fellows came running with Staves, and ſuch like miſchievous Weapons; which the Dr. perceiving, and finding that it was time to ſhift for himſelf, he made his retreat down <hi>Wood-ſtreet,</hi> and there got into a houſe, and ſo far prevailed with the people, that they ſhut the doors againſt the Rabble, who were by this time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed to 3 or 400. beſieging the houſe, and demanding the Dr. inſtantly to be delivered up to them, or elſe they would fire or pull it down; but the people a long time reſiſted them, and endeavoured to perſwade them to depart, in hopes that the Sheriffs would come with a power to receive the Dr. under a ſafe Conduct, but when they perceived all the Windows broak, and that the multitude had forced the outward door, and no hopes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54234:19"/> of any reſcue at hand, they were forced to deliver him up to ſave the ſpoiling of their Goods.</p>
               <p>When the Rabble had got him into their hands, ſome took him by the Legs, and others by the Armes, and ſo dragging him along the Streets, crying, <hi>Lamb, Lamb, the Conjurer, the Conjurer;</hi> every one kicking and ſtriking him that were neareſt.</p>
               <p>Now whilſt this Tumult laſted, and the City was in an Uproar, the News of what had paſſed came to the Kings ear, who immediately ordered his Guard to make ready, and taking ſome of the chief Nobility, he came in perſon to appeaſe the Tumult; when in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard he met the Inhumane Villains dragging the Dr. along, and after the <hi>Knight-Marſhal</hi> had proclaimed ſilence, who was but ill obeyed, the King, like a good Prince, mildly exhorted and perſwaded them to keep his Peace, and deliver up the Dr. to be Tryed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law, and that if his offence which they charged him with ſhould appear, he ſhould be puniſhed accordingly; commanding them to diſperſe and depart every one to his own home; but the Inſolent Varlets anſwered, That they had Judged him already, and thereupon pulled him Limb from Limb, or at leaſt, ſo Diſlocated his Joynts, that he inſtantly dyed.</p>
               <p>The King ſeeing no good was to be done with ſuch people, and wanting Forces ſufficient at that time to chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize their Inſolence, he returned to his Pallace, and in a while after ſent for the Heads of the City, as the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and blamed them exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly for not raiſing the power of the City to prevent the Murther of his Subject, and chaſtize the Inſolence of the Riotous Mortherers; but they excuſed themſelves, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they had no notice of it till ſuch time that the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude was too great to oppoſe; yet his Majeſty was ſo incenced, that he ordered Commiſſioners to inquire into
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54234:19"/> the matter, upon the return of whoſe Report, the City was Fined <hi>6000l.</hi> and on the <hi>16th</hi> of the ſame Inſtant, ſeveral were committed Priſoners that were preſent at the Riot; nor could the City appeaſe the Kings Anger, till ſuch time as they ſubmitted themſelves, and confeſſed their ſorrow for what had happened.</p>
               <p>As to the Inteſtine Tumults and Diſturbances, made by the City Uulgar, and thoſe that incenced them to ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural attempts as happened (during the Reign of this bleſt and for ever to be admir'd Monarch) I ſhall rather paſs them over in ſilence then inſiſt upon them, for as much as they will rather exaſperate mens minds, then any ways tend to the ſcope &amp; end for which this Treatiſe was written; for we doubt not but there formerly has been, and now are, as Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Worthy perſons Inhabiting the City, as any the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion affords; and therefore for their ſakes, I ſhall proceed no farther as to thoſe particulars.</p>
               <p>After the happy Reſtauration of His moſt Sacred Majeſty who now is, (whoſe Eſtabliſhed Throne may ever-wakeful Angels guard, and Heaven make his Reign long and happy over us, in ſpight of all the malice of his Foes) the City proſpered, &amp; to this day ſo well proſpers under the benign influence of ſo good a Prince, that no City in the World can boaſt the ſame; having received ſo many favours and Imunities from his Princely Bounty, that the like it has not for theſe 300 y. paſt been, received from any King of <hi>Engl.</hi> his Predeceſſor; therefore how grateful ought we to be to ſuch condeſcending Majeſty, and yet how little ſome regard the ſame.</p>
               <q>Ingratum ſi Dixeris omnia Dixeris.</q>
               <p>But to conclude, I ſhall only give the Reader a view of the Coppy of the Writt of <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> in Engliſh, as near as poſſible the Original Tranſlation from the <hi>Lattin</hi> will bear; which was ſerved upon the City, to inquire by what Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they lay claim to, and uſe, their Liberty, Franchiſes, and Priviledges, which take as followeth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
